foreign
it's July 15 2023
we're here in active inference model
stream number 9.1 with Aspen Paul
today we're going to have a presentation
and a discussion on efficient
computation in active inference so if
you're watching along live please feel
free to add comments or questions in the
chat otherwise
thanks so much for joining today really
looking forward to your talk
thank you Daniel thank you so much so as
mentioned today I'm going to talk about
efficient computation and active
inference and yeah let's get started
so we're all familiar with this idea of
the free energy principle which is also
known as active inference right so the
central concept is that an agent
minimizes entropy of its observation to
maintain homeostasis or survive in its
environment and here the entropy is
defined in the information theoretic
sense right so if an observation is
highly probabilistic that is less
entropic or less surprising because it
was high probability and we were
expecting it and
and and that that's the idea when that's
the base that we build this framework of
active inference on and this idea of
Marco blanket uh it gives us a
systematic way of surprising uh or the
schematic way of separating uh an agent
from its environment and model
purposeful Behavior right so let's focus
on this idea of minimizing entropy so
how does an agent minimize entropy or
know which observation is highly
probabilistic and vice versa
so that is by maintaining a generative
model and the generative model is
basically a toy model of the environment
which the agent builds in its brain and
that is built using only the observation
that it gets from the environment so it
has no access to the real uh States or
the hidden states of the environment
it's building the toy model and given
this toy model it has scope or ability
uh to compute the probability of an
observation and hence try to minimize
the entropy right so
that's the idea but it has a problem of
um cursive dimensionality like given a
generative model it may not be possible
always to calculate or marginalize the
probability of observations out of it
because the state space can quickly
become intractable but the idea is that
you define an upper bound on the
surprise using Jensen's inequality and
you may also
Define a new term called Q which is the
hidden belief or the belief about the
hidden States and this queue is going to
be the focus of decision making right so
if you have a noisy queue and you have
no idea what's in the environment then
you can't make or hope to make decisions
to control that environment and it is
this belief about the hidden states that
you use and that becomes useful to take
decisions and this whole quantity is of
course called the free energy and the
variational free energy
F can be interpreted in multiple ways so
the first or the most common is the
machine learning way of how it is
um Trying to minimize the complexity of
the model at the same time trying to
maximize the accuracy of it so that's
the machine learning interpretation of
minimizing various free energy you may
also try to
um
interpret free energy in the physics
term where you at the same time try to
minimize the energy of your model but at
the same time trying to maximize the
entropy but the focus of
today or decision making is always on
this belief that you have after you do
the perception in active inference so
how do you do vanilla decision making or
what is the most discussed idea of
decision making and classical active
inference uh so if you are in an
environment uh and if you're an agent
who's trying to make decisions then
you have a
space of available actions right so in
this toy model you have three available
actions uh run jump or stay and
given these actions you can hope to
define a policy by small Pi which is a
sequence of actions in time and capital
t is the time Horizon of planning or
that's the length of your
policy and you have a policy space with
many such policies small pie so given
this bigger smallest space you can
attempt to
evaluate the expected free energy based
on the beliefs that you have accumulated
so here you're not minimizing anything
you already have a belief from variation
for energy and you you are just
calculating or evaluating the expected
free energy corresponding to many uh
small policies that you can Define
and after you evaluate it for all
policies then you know which is the
optimal policy to take and that's the
classical active inference idea of
decision making right and
this expected free energy is really
useful in the sense that it is goal
directed so the risk term is goal
directed and then you have this expected
ambiguity term that forces you to
explore as well but there is a problem
that this policy space can quickly turn
interactable and that has always stayed
as a bottleneck in scaling active
inference to
um commonly seen environments but let's
see how it becomes quickly interactable
so how many policies can be defined say
for a Time Horizon of 15 right so if you
are playing say Super Mario uh you might
might want to plan at least say 10 time
step ahead so the first policy could be
um the same action run
um stacked for 15 time steps and you can
basically Define several combinations of
such actions and the policy space is
simply
um intractable it becomes uh too huge
for you to evaluate the expected free
energy for all such policies and in a
stochastic problem setting where
um the environment itself is noisy you
don't really have a method to choose a
subset of this policy space and do
classical active inference and this is
clearly a computational interactable
problem and that's why in literature we
always see small grids or small
environments when you discuss decision
making in active influence but recently
uh a new idea was
proposed which is called a sophisticated
entrance and in sophisticated inference
it is not really the policy space you
are actually
um real time trying to
think what to do so if you have a belief
then you are trying to
um evaluate the actions based on that so
here we don't have a sequence of
policies or things that becomes
interactable uh here we are doing
basically research in the sense that you
are trying to evaluate expected free
energy of um
this joint distribution of actions and
observations and to evaluate the
expected free energy at some time uh
small T you will also need the expected
free energy at the next time step and to
evaluate that you will need the expected
free energy of time t plus 2 and this
basically becomes a research that rolls
out in time and uh it's a it's a
recursive relation and
here it's fundamentally different from
the policy space that we saw in the last
slide right and
is it computationally better in the
sense that if you have to plan say 10
times tips ahead comprehensively in
classical active inference we saw that
the policy spaces
um
the cardinality of the action space
raised to T so that is the computational
bottleneck if you have to uh consider
all possibilities but in sophisticated
inference it's even worse because uh it
you are considering a combination of
state and actions so it is
computationally worse in fact but a
solution was proposed in the
sophisticated reference paper that we
can do pruning of This research that we
can avoid some states and actions uh
when you do this research and that
becomes computationally very tractable
so let's see how pruning Works in
sophisticated inference so this grid was
discussed in the original sophisticated
inference paper
and say for this grid given that you
have this kind of a prior preference
distribution so this white square which
is the goal status the most preferred
State and you have a
um
uniformly decreasing preference for
states that is far away from that gold
state then basically if You observe
yourself at some observation at time T
then basically what you're doing is
you're considering the consequence of
available actions from that observations
and basically you can use the projection
of your belief and set a threshold for
those beliefs to kind of maybe ignore
some actions and ignore some
observations and what you will find is
that it it's it's no longer at research
it's a subset of research and it's
computationally way uh efficient than
doing the whole research right so here
you have avoided a lot of combinations
and this becomes a computationally
attractable problem this is because you
have decided to avoid some actions and
um observation so you say essentially
compromising on that possibilities which
might give you a higher reward or which
might be more optimal than the
consequence of this partial research but
this works so this simulation
was presented in the paper and it works
the agent uh kind of learns to do uh
what needs to be done if it plans in
this forward direction of planning uh in
in a pruned way but
and
and basically you can computationally
show that even for a small search
threshold
um you can drastically decrease the
computational complexity so if you
decide to do the whole research
um with the planning depth uh the
computational time is exponential and
quickly you can't do much about it then
but if you decide at such threshold
which is even very small you can see
that this problem becomes
computationally attractable and this
demo uh on sophisticated instances are
available in my version of my mdp and
it's going to be integrated to the
original by mdp soon
um so
but the key point is that the pruning of
that research requires us a
well-informed prime preference like this
in the sense that here the agent is
aware of how desirable our neighboring
states it not only knows about the final
goal set it also knows about its
neighboring state and given such a prior
preference we can see that for a
planning depth of three the agent is
getting stuck basically in this local
Maxima of Prior preference but with
sufficient planning depth it is it is
able to overcome this barrier and reach
the goal State uh in in this great
problem and
the question is that what if the agent
only knows this final state it has no
other knowledge about what to do and in
this case what does the agent do so this
is the problem that we are trying to
address and in the absence of
a meaningful prior preference like this
the agent has basically no way of
reaching the goal State
um other than by random exploration it
it has no way of planning because it it
cannot do uh planning eight time steps
ahead because it's computationally
interactable uh if if it chooses to do
the full research right and
so if so for a grid like this what do
you do if you get a sparse try
preference which is not well informed
and as highlighted in the previous slide
your research is now blind uh you have
no way of pruning that research and you
have to do the full research in in this
scenario
so as you might have thought
um there are two solutions to this
either you have to find out a way to do
the full depth planning uh
or you have to learn a meaningful Pride
preference which will enable you to do
uh this pruned research so we are going
to discuss these two solutions uh in
this presentation uh for a given
scenario like this
so the first solution uh to do full
research is basically using dynamic
programming and dynamic programming is a
well-known idea in operation research
and industrial engineering and many in
many branches of engineering and the
basic idea is that you
solve the subparts of a bigger problem
first and then later try to integrate
the solutions of these sub problems uh
to do uh optimal decision making so
in this scenario imagine that
you're trying to plan for the Last
Action so earlier we started from the
first action we started from the present
and try to predict what is happening in
the future in in so your direction of
planning was basically forward in time
but imagine that you are trying to plan
only for the last time step where you
are just near the goal State and right
going to that good state right so you
are trying to make a decision for that
last time step which is capital T minus
1 and your projections uh to the next
time step or the last goal state will
um
can be done because you have access to
this model of the world uh using this
transition Dynamics or the B Matrix in
active inference so for this single time
step which is a sub problem uh you are
actually evaluating a table of expected
free energy that tells you if you are in
say this observation what is to be done
which is for the last time step and
basically uh you can do this in state
space or observation space so this can
be done uh using the a matrix and D
Matrix together where you can do
planning either way right so the
question is that
if you know what to do in the last time
steps
that you might be thinking how do I know
that I'm in the last time step it is all
about imagining you have
sorry just last thing we heard for a
second was it's all about imagining
yeah so just pick up from there it's all
about imagining
okay so if there was a connection issue
yeah just for a few seconds it's all
good then now
oh sorry about that but so
um so what I'm trying to say is that you
are trying to imagine what you will do
if you are in time capital T minus one
which is the last time step for your
planning Horizon and if you are in that
time step what do I do so this table
represents all such scenarios that if I
am say at observation 3 at time T minus
one what do I do and this quantity here
I'm only considering the risk term or
the purposeful term
uh and
this term represents that policy and
what if I do this
um backwards till time T minus one so if
I'm if I know what to do at time uh
capital T minus 1 then this table can
inform what to do at capital T minus 2.
so rather than planning forward in time
what I'm doing is basically stacking
many tables together just by fixing a
capital T of planning and
given that I have all such stack tables
then basically what I can do is use them
to take decisions forward in time and
what we have observed is that this idea
works that
um I can calculate the expected free
energy backwards uh step by step
considering them as sub problems and
the fundamental difference is that in
sophisticated inference uh to calculate
the expected free energy at time small T
you don't know what is the expected free
energy at time team plus one so this
becomes a three search so that you have
to calculate this first and to calculate
for t plus 1 you need t plus 2 and so on
but here because you are calculating it
backwards in time you already know what
is uh the expected free energy for p
plus 1 and you base it's basically the
same equation it's just that you're
doing it backwards in time and
pictorially in sophisticated inference
you are trying to do a research but in
the dynamic programming algorithm you're
doing your planning backwards uh using
tables and given your planning Horizon
is sufficient enough for a problem what
we have seen is that the agent will be
able to take optimal actions forward in
time so in the paper we are also
proposing uh one algorithm for
sequential form DPS using uh this
backward planning in time and we were
able to scale up simulations for grid
spaces which was previously interactable
without neural networks
um so that was the first solution
so the second solution is that
um so in the first solution it was fixed
that you only get this past private
reference you don't get any other
information you only get your
information about the final goal State
and all you get is the model of the
environment which you learned and you
basically have to take decisions but the
second solution of course is that if you
are allowed you can attempt to learn a
pride preference which is Meaningful
like the one we saw in the previous
slides which has the information about
the other states also but how do you
learn it right so
there is a seminal work from optimal
control literature that talks about
efficient computation of optimal actions
and in that work there is a quantity
similar to our prior preference which is
called the desirability function so for
example in this grid World
um here darker colors are more preferred
so if this crosses your final gold state
what the agent in this paper is trying
to do uh or the said learning method in
this paper is trying to do is learn this
desirability function as optimally as
possible and what has been shown in this
paper is that if you try to learn the
desirability function using a particular
learning rule it is computationally far
more efficient than even Q learning
which is a well-known uh reinforcement
learning algorithm so Q learning is a
well-known computationally optimal
algorithm but in this paper that
particular learning rule for learning
this kind of a desirability function is
way faster and this approximate
represents how different it is from the
optimal desirability function so this
desirability function is nothing but our
prior preference and
as mentioned learning said is borders of
magnitude efficient than learning the Q
function in Q learning so
this is the particular learning rule
depending upon the reward that it gets
from the environment and in this
particular grid World environment we are
only giving it reward at the last step
which is similar to the sparse friend
preference the agent basically gets no
reward uh until it reaches that final
goal State and with this learning rule
which which has a parameter ETA that
controls how fast or slow
this Learning Happens so basically we
try to
study the effect of this learning
parameter Rita but what we observed is
that it's very robust it can learn the
prior preference reliably even with
variable values of this uh learning
parameter and what we see is that the
agent is able to learn a meaningful
prior performance over time very fast
and using such a meaningful Prime
preference then the agent don't have to
plan a lot it can manage optimal
Behavior or purposeful Behavior with
very low time Horizons of planning and
given these two solutions we could scale
up active inference algorithm for
decision making and talking about the
computational efficiency uh we saw that
the dynamic programming method could
plant 30 time steps into the future uh
with only say a computational complexity
of thousand when compared to say 10 to
the power 68 for sophisticated inference
and the second method which learns the
prior preference uh which we call Active
inference and it only needs to plan one
time step ahead so it is way more
computationally efficient in that sense
but it has to learn so in the DPFE
method we are not learning we are using
the spots by preference and doing the
whole
depth of planning and in the other
method we are letting the agent learn
this by preference but then we can save
planning a lot because it knows a lot of
what to do in time right so
graphically we can see that um
the DPFE method is really
computationally efficient and when
plotted Against Time uh in the AI 50
equal to one method
um it is basically computationally
cheaper
and yeah so it scales uh very
fascinatingly well uh with Higher and
Higher and
complexity of the environment so we
tested it uh this these methods in
um
very huge State spaces like say 900
States
compared to
um State spaces which has dimension of
say 5 or 10 in the usually seen active
influence literature
um so I want to kind of emphasize that
we are not using any neural networks
here we are using um
explainable active inference agents are
doing all necessary matrix
multiplication so that we have access
and
um
explainability to every computation that
is taking place in this in these
algorithms and when tested on these
grids first we validated this on a
smaller grid with understates and we
observed is that
when compared to Benchmark reinforcement
learning algorithms like queue learning
and dynaq dynacy is a model based
reinforcement learning algorithm and we
compared our newly proposed agents which
is DPFE and aif and we saw really good
performance and aif agent is slightly
worse and that's because it's only
planning one time step ahead right but
the DPFE agent who does full time
planning it's performing as good as
benchmarking personal learning
algorithms and we tested it with um
bigger and weaker grids and when we
introduced stochasticity in the gold
state in the sense that when the agent
had to navigate to
um
stochastic gold state so we changed the
gold States at every 10 episodes and
what we observed is that the Dyna queue
took more time than our bpfe agent to
kind of recover and do well so DPFE
agent in this stochastic environment
performed really well even better than
the dynacy agents and you could also see
that the AI phase and is recovering um
faster but not as good as the other
agents so basically that was the result
in the paper and the methods So yeah
thank you for listening and I'm open for
discussions
all right awesome
wow
very cool
okay well just as we start the
discussion
um if anyone wants to add anything first
just how did you come to work on this
project uh were you studying active
inference and you came to this question
as being interesting or were you working
on the planning and came to active
inference as a method
um yeah so little bit background about
myself so I studied physics both in my
undergrad and post that and towards the
end of my post graduation I got
interested in things like Game Theory
and reinposable learning and I joined uh
for a joint PhD uh with Professor Adil
and Professor Manoj and so Professor
Manoj is a control theory person and a
deal is a neuroscientist and in the
beginning of my PhD I started reading
active inference literature and I wanted
to implement that in problems and I was
always fascinated with explainable
active inference uh about this idea of
expected free energy trying to minimize
risk as well as expected ambiguity it's
also not just making the agents work but
also being able to tell how they work is
what fascinated me in active influence
and initially I try to implement them
and there is a conference paper which we
published in which we compare it for a
similar gridual task and that then I
faced this problem of scaling active
inference and then I started working on
sophisticated inference
um yeah so basically these methods came
out of the need that I wanted to scale
the map up and I always had bus keptical
in using
um deep active inference because
um I didn't want to use neural networks
to do planning Because deep
reinforcement learning in itself is a
huge field and
um if you if you are about just scaling
active inference then maybe just do deep
reinforcement learning and that's what I
thought yeah so that's basically the
background and yeah
that's how it came about
all right I'll go first to a question in
the live chat and we'll just
probably discuss various aspects because
there was a lot in your presentation so
NL Dawn writes I wonder when it comes to
Computing the expected free energy over
a Time Horizon what kind of mean field
approximation was used to factorize Q of
s
store so
so I assume that the question is about
[Music]
the expected free energy in DPFE and
to calculate this basically
um
so in my simulations I use belief
propagation for this belief queue and
you can also also use variational
message passing or marginal message
passing that's not a problem but
so once you have this belief queue
um what do you do right
so
yeah so
when I say you imagine Q for a time then
what I use mostly is one hot Vector so
to take decisions you use the belief
that you get out of your perception step
in active inference but for imagining
these are hard tables where they are one
hot Vector so given say you have in your
generative model has 10 states uh your
the queues that you use are
um
precise cues for planning but for
decision making you use the impress
imprecise mean field approximation queue
that you get from the perception step so
I don't know if that answers the
question
um but maybe I I also want to think I
also need to think about more about the
approximations that may be there in the
steps
cool yeah they can they can write more
if they want um let's talk a little bit
more generally about preference learning
so in the context of the active
inference generative model we have a
mediating between observations in Hidden
States and learning makes
a lot of sense it's about learning the
mapping between observations in Hidden
states of the world and then we have
blearning learning the consequences of
action and how things change Through
Time
and preference learning is learning on c
c and you've highlighted that that this
is a very um
you know
interesting variable to learn
and I'm curious how does how do we learn
to learn the right thing how do we know
that we're learning an Adaptive
preference
and then how does that preference
learning reduce cognitive overhead or
computational complexity
yeah great
um so
if you are trying to learn a prayer
preference then that assumes that there
is something to Chase or there is
something to maximize like a reward so
in this say uh in a reinforcement
learning setting there is clear reward
that's coming from the environment that
you're trying to maximize and say for
this grid you get that reward only in
the last step that which is that that's
that's what makes this problem hard so
if you are getting rewards at every time
step then basically you know what to do
that I just have to pursue that reward
at every time step right but here you
might have to take say 15 time steps
ahead to get that one reward and that
basically is hard to do so here um if
you are trying because I'm trying to
learn a prior preference
um there should be a reward structure
that uh that exists in the environment
if the environment doesn't care about
what I do or if I can't Define what is
good or bad then there is no meaning in
learning the prior preference right so
here
um the reward is what controls the
learning of the Sprite difference and
the good thing is that even if only I
get the reward at the last time step
um I have my B matrices and I have
experience of transitioning from
different states
um which I reached this final gold state
and
this algorithm that we are using or the
learning rule that we are using is
precisely learning a similar thing in
optimal control that paper I introduced
which is called the desirability
function and given that you have this
desirability function so imagine that
maybe I am starting from this state then
I just have to look at my nearest
neighbors to take a decision
if the stated
um State below the state is more
preferred than I only have to plan one
time instead ahead and that's the
optimal decision I have to take
so learning this Pride preference
reduces the cognitive load in the sense
that I'm only now looking at nearest
neighbors I don't have to plan all the
way up to this final good state
and I will learn this as efficiently as
possible because one it was it is a
guaranteed algorithm we tested its
robustness and it is also informed by
the reward that I get from the
environment and
if yeah so if there is some way uh to
kind of Define what is preferred uh then
you are guaranteed to learn a private
friends that's meaningful
by this algorithm
so if only nearest Neighbors
and one time step inference is being
used then what prevents this kind of
preference learning agent from being
stuck in a local Optima
um yeah so there won't be local Optimas
here that's the point like
um why would there be a local Optima uh
if I am learning it using rewards uh
yeah so if if there is local Optima then
it will be getting stuck in the local
Optima but there won't be one uh if
you're learning is this way because
you're learning it from your own
experience and how you got the reward at
time uh sometime and what we have
observed is that uh it's very
um
gradual and there is no glitches or
local Optimas when you learn such as
so it's kind of back filling a
preference
so that there can be a smooth path
yeah to the distal goal
yes so it in the animation kind of makes
it look like a back feeling but
um you're actually learning it from your
experience
um
forward in time right so I observed a
reward when I transitioned from this
state to the state so this must be good
uh then the in the in the next time step
I say okay this date is responsible for
taking me there so this might be good
also but not as good as the other one
so it looks like it's learning backwards
but it's actually learning from the real
um into t plus one experience
okay
you know so in that way
um you can't have local Maximas because
um
yeah this is the learning rule that does
that so I don't know how to answer it
more systematically yeah yeah
um what what real world situations or or
what real life situations do you kind of
see this kind of preference learning
happening in
yeah
great question so
so there is one paper that came out from
our lab where neurons are laying
learning the game of pong
um so there was so if the paper is
called dist brain uh and the device is
called strain and what they have
accomplished is that they manage to
culture neurons
on a silicon chip and they
um
gave it a good uh feedback signal when
it successfully tackled the ball or
played the game well and gave it a shock
uh when
um it made mistakes and what we saw is
that
in the paper what we see is that it
learns to play the game over time right
and in in such a scenario imagine that
if I encounter say a positive thing in
the world then I might associate
um what is good with the states I
observed in the past and so on right so
I learned
um
step by step what is good or bad and
that's a reasonable hypothesis to make
so if
um
if I want to say get fitter then I might
associate going to gym
um
as a good thing then I might also
associate walking to the gym as a good
thing then I might associate uh say
wearing my shoes as a good thing so
um
learning prior preference that way makes
sense I would say but yeah this is a
computational
um
solution to the problem of curse of
dimensionality but testing this on the
real world is definitely uh what we
should do and
um yeah I also look forward to doing
that
okay let me let me try to run a real
world situation by you and see if this
if this connects
um so we wanna we want to turn in we're
rewarded by turning in an essay that
gets a high grade
and so there's many steps between
starting the idea of the essay and
seeing that preferred sparse outcome
which is the grade
um and we we do all kinds of things and
then we learn okay well
um this one where I did get a good grade
it was well formatted
and then that kind now you sort of
expand the umbrella of your preference
out and then what brought me to getting
it well formatted well I did it on time
and then you kind of work all the way to
the ideation phase so that in the future
you can do one step inference yes
exactly and just take it step by step as
a skill
instead of needing to do
a 15 time step
inference over all the possible tree
structures so you've kind of used your
embodied learnings to simplify the
structure of the problem exactly yeah
and can we look at the computational
complexities
um again of the of all them
so here CIF stands for the classical
active inference and to do the full
Horizon of planning
um it's around 10 to the power 18. so
this is for this particular grid example
with 100 States and four available
actions so this is for a special case
and I just wanted to put numbers to put
things in perspective so for this
particular example if you are trying to
do it with the policy space thing
um you will have to do
um 10 to the power 18 computations for
one step of planning or in one
um instance in sophisticated inference
it's even worse because uh there you go
the state space Also matters uh and that
won't work so this third line was
supposed to kind of show that even for a
time
um or rise enough two it's really hard
to do sophisticated inference if you
have to do the full planning but with
dynamic programming when you're planning
backwards
um you can attempt to do the full
Horizon of planning
um and that's only a thousand
computations but with learning
preference it's even low uh when you do
it just one time Step Ahead
wow this is quite
[Music]
um
quite Stark and in the branching time
active inference work in a previous
model stream we also saw some
computational complexity estimates but I
think these are really clear
um first thing it made me think of is
no one said sophistication was cheap
I mean it's it's astronomical how costly
it is for
um maybe even only at two or three or
four or five
potentially starting to get up to so
it's increasing the the complexity of
planning
um radically so it's very
um
interesting
pedagogically as we think about like as
we imagine
active inference intelligence
architectures
but
this makes it pretty clear that it's not
something that you can just enumerate
over
and so I think it's very
um very creative and important what
you've done by connecting this to
principled methods of computational
complexity reduction rather than
potentially effective but ad hoc methods
of complexity reduction like neural
networks which might work when they work
but then once those start to get bloated
now you have no principles and no
efficacy
exactly yeah and sophisticated inference
I must note that has its own benefits
when compared to dynamic programming uh
in the sense that when you're planning
forward you are taking into
consideration all the possibilities
right but when you're planning backwards
say for example it's like cue based
exploration
um like if you have to go somewhere get
a queue and then navigate to the pool
State then planning backwards might not
work so this is what this was one
feedback I got and I discussed uh the
work with
um some people so
um that's a thing to note about dynamic
programming but the other place where
you learn prior to friends I believe
it's not a problem but yeah dynamic
programming is computationally cheap but
it also come with its own limitations I
must note here
just to restate that in dynamic
programming with a Bellman optimality
we're solving backwards and so it's kind
of like the Checkmate is what we want
and so now we're working backwards to
the present but we end up not exploring
counterfactual
end points we don't work back to the
present to end points that we're not
interested in
exactly so that's why it's so ruthless
but on the other hand it's a much more
constrained
um
search yes so yeah so what I'm thinking
about these days is that we should also
consider uh combinations of these two uh
where I can afford to kind of ignore
such counterfactual things
um there I can do dynamic programming uh
and maybe I can do as two steps uh of
planning so if it's a queue based
exploration uh say reaching queue uh is
one task and from queue to the reward is
the other task so I can separate these
two and use dynamic programming for them
and that's computationally cheaper but
also kind of preserves this idea of
um having to do it yeah but these are
all future things I am thinking about
cool or ask another question from the
chat Alex wrote
do you have ideas or developments on
nested models where different scales
could have different
[Music]
um
one time step ahead and speed of
execution
so how does this model play out in
nested models
and how how do we think about this
forwards and backwards in time in the
speed of execution and nested models
okay so I might need a little more
context here like
um when you say nested models um do you
mean hierarchical models yeah
yeah so maybe
um something like there is a observation
I get on a fast pace and I do some
inference on that but then I use this
inference uh to kind of do
or maybe uh and that basically this
inference becomes the observation for
the next state and that's what nested
models mean right yes so I might have to
actually think about that in terms of a
task and then think about it but
honestly I I haven't
um thought how this might work in that
context but say for a task
um
like uh so in terms of navigation if you
think about it you can think about
um
say rooms environment so that's where uh
that's one of the examples I can think
about where we can apply this so imagine
maybe you have a collection of rooms and
as an agent you have to first figure out
which room to go and then you have to
navigate inside that home and basically
you can do uh inference in two stages or
decision making in two stages uh and you
have you will have to separate your
decisions in in those stages
inside the room you can do say dynamic
programming to navigate your optimal uh
path but you will always have to kind of
have two stages of
um decision making and um
maybe different methods work better at
different stages but this would be uh
better in you know I mean this
discussion would be better to
um
better in in a well
thought out task I would say I I don't
have a answer that might be fitting for
everything but
yeah
yeah we've seen almost exactly that kind
of hierarchical simultaneous
localization and mapping Slam in a
robotics case there have been active
inference models on that
um yeah would it be possible to sort of
do
um one of these methods
at one level of the nested model and
then have another computational method
applied to another
um or is like if you wanted the
advantages of one in one place like can
you mix and match with these different
methods even within one simulation
yeah I I I definitely think that's
possible
um but yeah we'll have to maybe try
so all my methods are um one stage so
it's not a hierarchical model
and but I I strongly believe that it
would also work in an estate model where
you can have
um two methods of decision making
working together in say for a room
example I just mentioned
oh could you go to the slide on Z
learning
cool yeah so I noticed um here and in
the great paper that you had several
total of citations yes and so and this
introduction of the Z learning is is a
novelty with respect to the active
inference field so could you explain a
little more
what is the Z
and what is it that enables such a a
rapid
um
Improvement in the Z with respect to the
Q
yeah okay so uh to give some context
um context about this paper
um
it's it talks about a
linear method of decision making uh in a
particular class of mdp so given that
you are having a Markov decision process
where your actions can be based on
States and not accents so when you think
about actions in a say in for example a
gridual task
you think about left right and
um North South right so if I take a
north then that has a consequence of uh
consequence on state space but in this
paper
um they're introducing a class of mdp
where decision is itself in terms of
states
so if I am saying State S1 my decision
will be uh
depending upon the other state so my
decision will be based on the other
states I want to be in the next time so
uh
it's a really definition of decision
making uh in terms of the state space
rather than decisions being something
else like left right and down up
so given that
such an mdp exists where I can take
decisions in terms of states
they have showed that computationally
you can take uh decisions in linear
complexity however big the problem is
so for that to so to enable decision
making in terms of States you should
have a sense of what is good and bad for
the states
so in this gridward example uh you have
a desirability function which is C so C
is the desirability function
which talks about how desirable is a
state and if I have a c function then
what they have showed is that
um
I can take decisions with linear
computational complexity for this
particular class of mdp so if my mdp
allows me to take decisions in terms of
States it's linearly uh it's it's only
linear complexity for that thing
so this graph is basically comparing how
you can learn desirability uh better
or faster right so Q learning if you are
familiar with Q learning it's basically
a table based method uh where you have
um desirability of actions given a state
so given a state you know what to do
that's basically the queue Matrix but in
terms of C
uh or the C learning method it's only
about States uh you're only learning how
desirable a state is there is no concept
of actions
and this is exactly what our prior
preference uh is in active inference
where it is a distribution that
quantifies how desirable or
non-desirable states are
right so
given that they have shown that you have
you can learn the C Matrix faster and
that's optimal and it's way faster than
even Q learning then I thought okay why
not try to learn C the same way as C is
learned in this paper and
using this say so there is a similar
learning rule for learning C which is
called set learning in that paper and
when I attempted to learn see what I've
seen is that it learns really fast a
useful Pride preference that lets me
take decisions or let the active
influence agent take decisions
um only by say one time step of planning
and yeah so basically that took the
story so
um
this idea of C being easily learnable is
in that paper
okay let me try to um restate that since
I think it's a very interesting
augmentation of active inference so
we're going to be learning C
for all the
reasons we discussed earlier
we're going to learn C
analogously to how todorov presented Z
learning and in the Z learning
instead of learning
um for example updated posterior
probabilities on actions
and then using actions to navigate
amongst states that emit observations
yeah we're going to kind of bake the
action
into the states
so that really we're learning
transitions among states
directly yeah
and and to connect this to the free
energy principle and and how it is
playing out with with active inference
here
um
C is not just our desirability function
that's one way of thinking about it
that's why we call it preference but
also C is our expectation and so that is
what allows us to on one hand use the
language familiar to reward and
preference learning like the agent is
ending up where it likes to be but also
the expectation based
um definition of c these are the same
thing allows us to talk about that as a
path of least action or as the most
likely outcome or the least surprising
outcome and because we've defined it
what we want as the least surprising
outcome then we can use variational free
energy to bounce surprise whereas you
can't use simply a variational method to
bound or even necessarily approximate
reward itself
but if you say
I prefer what I expect
and what I expect reduces my surprise
and I'm going to balance surprise
then you get both that sort of
Behavioral reward seeking
couched in a surprise bounding surprise
minimizing physics framework
yeah yeah that's a beautiful way of
saying it yeah thank you
well what are your um next uh
exciting
steps or directions or what what ways do
you want to take this work yeah great
yeah so
um if you're talking about only this
work
um what I want to do next is uh
think about cue based exploration tasks
I first of all address the limitations
of dynamic programming so it's if you
have say a queue to explore in this grid
first and that's more optimal I want to
see how the uh expected ambiguity term
in the expected free energy is useful
and should be made use in the dynamic
programming
strictly in that sense
um but more generally I'm also looking
at other ways of making decisions in
active influence like there are works
from Professor
a summer
from CBS reckon he talks about how it's
How neural networks are doing active
inference and basically decision making
there is
um really uh more efficient in the sense
that it's like queue learning so in
there he's making clever use of the
variation free energy to learn good
State action mappings and it's it's a
very drastic
um change to what we are used to in
terms of expected free energy so there
is no concept of expected free energy uh
in in that work it's all about learning
what is good and bad directly from
variation for energy so I I find that
also fascinating I want to kind of
explore that more and see how decision
making uh in this way is better or worse
or should be thought about should we
even reconsider ways of decision making
because active inference only talks
about variational free energy and that's
the central tenet everything else is
your interpretation of that right
so yeah
that's another Direction I want to work
interesting way to say it um definitely
the variational free energy which is a
functional of our variational
um distribution q and the data y
the variational free energy is kind of
like the real time
homeostasis like yeah how are things
making sense given what I believe and
the incoming data
and then to extend that kind of a
sense-making framework into decision
making we've seen a lot of different
methods expected free energy is
um a common one but for example there's
been free energy of the expected future
as eef and there's other constructions
that have different methods
um and then you point it also to
Professor samura's work
with um the sort of uh
relationship between the variational
free energy on the base graph and the
loss function in a neural network and
all those relationships that's very
exciting work too
um I guess kind of in closing just as a
last question or thought
you're coming close to the end of your
PhD
so just in the time that you've been a
PhD student
how have you seen active inference
develop or what what
feels different to you today near the
end than when you were
yeah fresh-eyed and excited several
years ago
yeah that's that's a really great
question and uh I am also very excited
of how the field has evolved and frankly
I started from this reinforcement
learning background and the physics
background and when I started reading it
was only say one or two papers and I did
not quite understand much of it uh it
was only when I started uh implementing
it using calls
um Matlab scripts I kind of understood
okay this makes sense and I like it and
but within uh say one or two years I saw
a lot of papers coming in uh from
different directions and people also
starting to use neural networks and all
this scaling up came and I I at some
point I also questioned the need of
active inference uh because if you have
deep reinforcement learning can which
can do many things then why deep active
inference and that's the reason why I
did not get into that but I still find
it fascinating I want to kind of
understand deep active inference more
than what I know now but I've seen the
field growing like anything in in two or
three years and many cohorts of people
starting to work and in no time it was a
seriously taken field other than a field
with say two papers with nobody actually
knowing what it is so it's really
exciting yeah so I really look forward
how the field evolves in time and also
what I can do after my PhD and so on
cool forward in time backward in time
what we prefer what we expect yes
any other
comments or anything else you want to
add
yeah so please let me know what you
think about the paper and what you think
about these ideas feel free to let me
know I I really look forward to the
feedback and
yeah thanks so much for this opportunity
Daniel and thank you for your time
it was amazing I hope people um check
out the paper and and get in touch and
replicate the code and and take it their
own directions thank you
see you next time
see you next time thank you so much bye
have a good day bye